we're gonna go through quite a lot of
material today and a bit of it will be
reviewed but not very much okay so we've
started with this fundamental
propositions here that you're viewing
the world through a narrative framework
and the narrative framework basically
lays out the world for you as a place in
which you can act and the reason that
you act is to make the state that you're
in current that the state that you're
moving to next better than the state
you're in now now part of the reason
that I had you write about your past was
because the early cognitive scientists
sort of took it for granted that your
model of where you are now wasn't
actually a model it was just reality
because you look out in the world and
you can see the reality and there you
are
but that's not true because because
you're you're you're as constrained with
regards to the information that you have
at hand about the present just as much
as you are about the future or the past
then your your conceptualization of the
present is also a model just like your
conceptualization of the future and the
reason that's so important to know is
that if when you're moving from point A
to point B you make an error the error
could be that you've predicted the
future or construed the future
inaccurately but it could also be that
you've construed the present or the past
inaccurately and what that means is that
you didn't start from where you thought
you were starting you know and that
happens for example that will happen if
you're moving forward and you discover
that you have weaknesses of one form or
another that you didn't know about when
you made the original plan and that what
that means is that you're your current
conception of yourself is sufficiently
inaccurate so that you can't move from
that conception to the future desired
state without error and the other reason
I'm telling you that is because one of
what that also helps you understand is
how broad the domain of potential error
is when something you don't understand
happens because not only does it throw
the future that you're conceptualizing
into doubt it also throws the
conceptualization of you as a being in
the present into doubt and it's not
obvious at all when you do
the initial search we're in which of
those domains you're going to find the
error or where and so it's error is a
more complex problem than the than the
cognitive scientists who are interested
in the comparator models of of
cybernetic processing hadn't had ever
conceptualize because they thought they
kind of thought in behaviorist terms
which is while the world just presents
itself to you as it is so you're not
going to be making any errors of
fundamental perception you just might be
making errors of prediction but that's
far too optimistic now we also know that
this fundamental narrative framework
which gives you a sense of the value of
your current position and the
destination because you're a moat you're
a moving creature you're an active
living creature that's interacting with
the world and transforming it all the
time
there's also there are also constraints
on which the narrative that you're going
to conceptualize and act out can exist
and the constraints are well they're
piagetian constraints in some sense
whatever it is that you're doing has to
support you while you're doing it that's
constraint number one and that means
that your your the path you take has to
fulfill whatever constitute the list of
necessities that you can't move forward
without and some of those we think of as
basic needs like you have to breathe and
you have to eat and you have to have
sufficient you have to have sufficient
water you have to have shelter and all
those things and there's a you know the
parameters within which those needs can
be fulfilled are pretty broad but you
know so you can't think of it
necessarily as a simple problem or that
there are simple solutions but there's
still obvious constraints and not only
do you have to fulfill all those
fundamental obligations to yourself but
you have to do it in a manner that's
relatively noncontradictory so that
while you're pursuing one it doesn't
decrease the chance that you're going to
obtain another and you have to do it in
a way that the way you do it now doesn't
compromise you doing it
next week or next month or next year
that's where delay of gratification
comes in and then you also have to do it
in a way that fulfills your basic needs
in a non contradictory manner over
different spans of time and space while
other people are doing the same thing
and so you think see that's a very very
tight set of constraints and so the idea
that that that this narrative could be
anything is wrong because it it it has
to serve many masters simultaneously and
I'm not saying there aren't multiple
solutions to that just like there are
multiple ways of playing or winning a
game but it's a constrained set of
possibilities so okay now the next
proposition is that when you're moving
from point A to point B there's
basically there's two or three classes
of things that can happen one is things
that you don't want to have happen and
that obviously is symbolically
represented by the little blue unhappy
face and then there are positive things
that can happen and the positive things
are twofold in nature they have two
fundamental elements and behaviorists
never tell you this so it's one of the
fundamental flaws in behavioral theory
things that indicate that you're moving
towards a desired goal are positive
that's classic sophisticated behavioral
theory those are incentive rewards
because an incentive reward indicates to
you that a consuming Tory reward is
forthcoming and there are different
neurobiological systems that underlie
those two types of reward consumed
Ettore reward basically produces
satisfaction whereas incentive reward
produces excitement hope and movement
forward and it's actually the kind of
reward that you like better which is
weird you know because you think that
the most potent reward would be consumed
Ettore reward but people will work
harder for incentive reward than they
will for consuming Tory reward and
that's that's one of the things that
makes people very peculiar creatures and
I think part of the reason for that is
that the incentive reward system is part
of the broader seeking system
Jacque panksepp describes it and so
because the incentive reward system not
only tells you that a reward like an
expected reward might be forthcoming it
also tells you that an unexpected reward
might be forthcoming and the reason
that's so important is because you
actually view the world that you don't
understand partly through the lens of
threat because of something that you
don't understand happens it might be
dangerous but also through the lens of
possibility because if something you
don't understand happens that means
there's an indeterminate probability of
reward and like these things turn out to
be extremely important so for example if
you're in a long-term sexual
relationship with a person the degree to
which that relationship might be
sexually pleasurable will decline and
they're part of the reason for that is
that there's the novelty disappears
because novelty enhances incentive
reward and so one of the things that you
can do to maintain the romance in a
relationship is to mix some novelty and
however you might be able to do that and
that usually involves playing in one
form or another and a certain amount of
creativity so it's not a trivial issue
it's an important issue so anyways when
when you're moving forward and you
encounter something that indicates that
you're going to achieve your goal the
other thing that's happening at the same
time is that the fact that that thing
appears validates your entire perceptual
scheme right so a you're moving forward
to the goal but B the whole plan that
you're using to construe the world in
order so that you can act so that you
can move towards the goal is also
sufficiently right and that's a big
source of incentive reward
not only your conception of the present
but the whole framework itself your
conception of the present the future and
your choice about what behaviors to
implement yeah yeah okay yep yeah oh no
definitely not as you move towards the
goal things you don't want and things
you do want might be happening and like
if something you don't want happens then
it depends on the it depends on the
relationship of the thing that didn't
happen to your whole goal hierarchy and
the problem is and that's where we're
going to go next is when the unexpected
thing happens unless it's very simple
which means that it can be modified here
and now with very little disruption then
it has an incalculable effect on the
integrity of the entire plan and that's
that's why unexpected things in
particular are a class in of their own
now it's complicated a because normally
when you're moving towards a goal if any
obstacle appears it's unexpected
obviously because partly what you're
trying to do when you lay out a good
plan is to make sure that the pathway
doesn't have any obstacles in it so you
almost never encounter just like you
never encounter an incentive reward
without also encountering a piece of
evidence that your plan is good you
never encounter an obstacle without also
encountering evidence that your plan is
flawed and then the question is well how
flawed and that's the big question and
that's why there's a third category of
events that occur as you're laying your
plans
as you're laying your plans out in the
world and implementing them and that
category is things you didn't expect
so not merely obstacles but they're
things you didn't expect so now that's
what this diagram basically indicates so
as you're moving from The Unbearable
present it's unbearable because you want
to make it better which is also
something to think about when you're
considering why human beings are
constantly dissatisfied it's like well
if you weren't vaguely dissatisfied with
the present you wouldn't be doing
anything to try to change it into the
future and so there's a certain amount
of vague dissatisfaction that's actually
a necessary motivator now you know you
hope that there are times when you think
things are good enough for right now so
you can take a break from constantly
walking uphill but you can also see that
if you were completely satisfied we know
this from from animals like lions you
know after a kill all the Lions news lay
around until they've digested all the
food you know and they're probably
satisfied but it isn't obviously the
case that that's the best possible
strategy so as you're moving from the
unbearable present to the desired future
you can think that positive things
happen so those facilitate your movement
forward and negative things happen and
that interferes with your movement
forward or you can think differently you
can which is a slight
reconceptualization you can say that
predicted things happen and that
unpredicted things happen so that's just
that's a slightly different shift right
because when you talk about unexpected
and expected obviously you're not
referring to something that's only a
manifestation in the actual world it's
also a relationship that you have with
the thing in the world because expected
means not only does it happen but you
knew it was going to happen whereas
unexpected means not only does it happen
but you didn't know so there's a
subjective element and then you could
change that another way to because and
this is I think the most accurate way to
think about it which is it's not
expected and unexpected it's desired and
undesired and
there the utility in making that
transformation is it brings motivation
into the picture
you're never only expecting or not
expecting you're wanting and not wanting
yeah yes sort of if you lay out a good
plan you may say well here's 10 things
that I don't want to have happen that a
relatively high probability and then you
could build a little sub plan around
each of those that constitutes a micro
strategy within the plan but the way -
the way to conceptualize that
effectively is to think about this this
isn't you don't have a plan ever you
have a nested series of plans and you're
operating at one level of that nested
series at a time now if the if that
expected if it's an expected undesirable
thing it usually affects a micro element
of the plan right and so that you can
change that and fix it without too much
effort if it's a macro element you know
let's say okay you fail of course that's
one thing another thing is east-european
cyber criminals hijack your hard drive
and encode it and they charge you
$10,000 to decode it and then you don't
have enough money to go to university
it's like okay well which of those
events is more serious well obviously
failing the exam is not a positive event
it's a it's a somewhat unexpected event
likely if you were doing the work but it
doesn't blow apart your entire plan
whereas the the the theft of all your
resources is a macro failure not only do
you are you not getting from point A to
point B but the the framework within
which you're conceptualizing point a and
B is wrong but it might even be worse
than that
it's a superordinate framework that
blows apart ten or eleven different
plans so
it's that it's complicated because
things are never only predicted and
unpredicted they're desired and
undesired and then they're desired and
undesired to different degrees and the
degree depends on the place in the
hierarchy where the unexpected thing is
doing the disruption so but you there's
no way of getting towards that level of
description without starting off as if
you're only implementing one plan at a
time so this is a this is an
oversimplification that's necessary
before we develop a sophisticated idea
of of how it is that you're interacting
with the world okay so a desired outcome
that's an incentive reward it makes you
hopeful and positive and alert and
energetic and willing to move forward
it's what you want it's what you want
it's a dopaminergic reaction
fundamentally whereas if something that
you happen that happens that you don't
want
well that's both threatening technically
because you it it indicates that a
punishment is likely and you don't
necessarily know the magnitude of the
punishment and it's also punishing in
and of itself so those are all that's
obviously a category that you don't want
to have happen and the other problem is
it's not easy to bind it you know so
look at it this way you have a
relationship with someone and it's kind
of conflict Laden you know and you think
each time you have a conflict you think
should I be in this relationship well
that's a big problem because you
actually don't know how much conflict
should you have before you shouldn't be
in a relationship and the answer to that
is well you don't know now there's
actually some empirical work on the
topic so I can give you a provisional
answer which is quite interesting so
there was a research psychologist a
while back who I thought did a brilliant
study and they had couples record
positive events just qualitatively how
many positive interactions did you have
with your partner during the day versus
how many negative interactions don't
think they quantified the degree to
which they were positive and negative
they're just going to assume that across
multiple
instances that would wash out and what
they found was it's quite cool they
found that if you had fewer than five
positive interactions to every negative
interaction the relationship was going
to collapse so now you can start
counting and see if that's appropriate
to you but the other thing they found
which I thought was really lovely was
that if you had more than eleven
positive interactions to one negative
interaction the relationship was also
doomed and so you think so you
understand that right yet everyone knows
that because if someone's wandering
around treating you like a god too
regardless the first thing you're going
to do is be just contemptuous of them
and then completely bored you want the
person to harass you a bit just so that
you learn something that's part of it so
but so it's also evidence that there's
actually someone there that you're
interacting with you know because if
someone just does everything you want
all the time well I mean that might
sound like an ideal fantasy but you know
perfectly well that if that ever
happened that's just you're just gonna
get completely tired of that instantly
plus there's no there's no life in the
relationship right which is a big issue
so yes right right right well exactly
well the other thing too is you can be
sure that in a relationship where
there's no conflict nothing is being
decided because thought is conflict even
if you do it by yourself you know and so
if there are two of you in a boat and
you're trying to decide where you're
going in the future it's not like that
self-evident there has to be some you
have to have an opinion and your partner
has to have an opinion and there's no
reason at all to assume that those
opinions are there will be or should be
the same and then you know you hope the
relationship is solid enough so that it
can withstand the tension of the
conflict one of the things you've said
about marriage which I thought was
because you can get a very nice job of
trying to understand from a
psychological perspective why in the
world you should bother being married
which is really a very interesting
question you know and one of the things
one of the things he said was that you
don't need to tie two things together if
they'll just stay together
of their own accord
the fact that marriage is a human
Universal which it is indicates that
there is enough tension within intimate
relationships
centrifugal tension to blow them apart
and some of that's just because people
are different and they clash but it's
also because as you go through life in a
single boat you encounter huge waves and
you know you might get swamped so it's a
big problem his point was that the
marriage vow was necessary because if
your response to potential conflict was
I can leave you can't have the conflict
you can't have the conflict you know if
if on the other hand you're with someone
and you think there's no bloody way I
can get rid of you no matter what I do
short of murder I'm stuck with you for
the next 30 years then we better work
this out and so that makes the he
thought of that as a container within
which a transformation could take place
it was no chemical motif and that
without that pressure people weren't
going to be sufficiently motivated to
really hash out problems and you know
you can think of that think of that in
whatever way you want but I thought it
was an absolutely brilliant observation
well the problem is it doesn't solve a
pro it doesn't solve any problems
usually because for a variety of reasons
one is it's probably you and not your
partner anyways or at least there's a
50/50 chance and if it's you you're just
gonna bring your stupidity to the next
relationship and torture someone else to
death you know so that's a big problem
the next problem is is that if you can't
work out the bugs in this relationship
why do you think you're going to be able
to do it in the next relationship
especially now that you're older and
more set in your ways
the third is well you know what about
the kids
the fourth is I don't know if you've
ever seen people in a protracted custody
battle but if you want to ruin your life
that's a really good way of doing it
because that'll take you out for about
15 years and it'll cost you pretty much
all your money and it'll destroy your
your closest relationships and I'll also
make it four
actually impossible for you to be happy
with the next person that you're with
because they're gonna be you know
burdened by this absolute catastrophe
that's surrounding you with regards to
how you organize your into relationships
with the people that you love so so
generally speaking I don't think that it
I don't think that it usually solves the
problem now it's sometimes it does but
my sense is it's probably introduced
more problems than it solves
you know so I mean one of the things you
might note for example is that the only
people who now get married are people
who are relatively wealthy you know the
fact that we've disrupted the structure
of marriage as an institution since
about 1965 say what that's meant what
that has meant is that it's its benefits
are now only available to people who
were privileged so you can look up the
stats yourself but if you're middle
class and above the divorce rates
haven't moved much since the early 70s
if you're working class and below it's a
complete catastrophe and what that's
meant is that most many children who are
in rougher socio-economic straights
are being raised by a single person who
is absolutely and 100% overwhelmed by
their multiple commitments right
full-time responsibility for children
and generally in employment in an
extraordinarily dismal low-paying
unstable and exploitative job so to me
if you if you're like you guys are
you're all gonna be middle class or
above in all likelihood it's like it's
fine for you it's not gonna make a
bloody bit of difference all things
considered but for people who are poor
it's just being a catastrophe so okay so
yes
oh wow there's all sorts of reasons I
mean first of all it's become socially
acceptable right divorce wasn't socially
acceptable and you can say well that's
that was pretty hard on people who
wanted to get divorced it's like yeah
obviously any rule is hard on people
that break it but that doesn't mean that
there shouldn't be rules you know
now what rules there should be that's a
whole different issue out of wedlock
childbirth has become a norm
it was absolutely rare in the 1919 60s
vanishingly rare and that's become it's
it's acceptable even though all the
evidence suggests like if you actually
look at the evidence it's absolutely
clear that kids who have two parents do
better than kids who have one now you
know people when you tell people that
they'll tell you an anecdote about
someone they knew maybe their own parent
who did a wonderful job of raising them
as a single person it's like the
anecdotes are irrelevant
what what's relevant is the bulk of the
evidence of course there are situations
where people are better apart than
together and of course there are
situations where one person can do a
better job than two people who were out
each other's throats but it's it's
aggregate it's aggregating examples that
you use when you're doing a scientific
survey and the results of those surveys
are crystal clear you know the other
thing that's going to happen it's going
to happen very soon is that there is
going to be a very very very very large
number of elderly people who are alone
and being elderly and alone like no
family that is not something you want to
look forward to especially when you
start thinking that you're gonna be
elderly for like 40 years so you know
because say say it starts around 65 I
don't know how long you guys are gonna
live but it's probably 95 is not an
unreasonable estimate and it might be
longer than that so because you know
we're adding about three months to the
total life span every year right that's
the rate of technological improvement in
relationship to overall mortality so you
know and that the degree to which we're
adding that extra
lifespan is increasing each year you
know and it may hit get to the point
where we're increasing lifespan a year
every year now I doubt it cuz it'll
probably eat it'll probably be in a city
a sim tote but it has been increasing
for a very long period of time so you
know it's one thing to think about the
maximization of day to day freedom when
you're between say 15 and and 4045 after
that that's a whole different story and
but modern people never think about the
last half of their life you know so why
I don't know but maybe they're afraid
too or something but okay so here the
other way of looking at it is when
you're no so there's lots of ways of
conceptualizing what you encounter when
you move into the world so we said well
you know there's positive things you
encounter negative things there's
expected things and unexpected things
there's desired things and undesired
things and another way of thinking about
it which is more in some sense it's more
empirical is that you encounter tools
and obstacles right and tools move you
forward and tools are a funny thing
because they're sort of half objective
and half subjective right they're a
thing but the thing is defined by their
use but weirdly enough we tend to define
thing by use you know and I mentioned
this before so most people when they're
thinking about language think that you
use words to label things but it seems
much more likely that we use categories
as tools to act in the world and so we
don't see things we see the use of
things or the fact that they get in our
way
and so you're trying to set up the world
so that what surrounds you are entities
that you can use to get what you desire
and to eliminate obstacles and in fact
that's what you generally do if you're a
good manager right a big part of being a
good manager is to first of all lay out
a plan for people that's hierarchy and
and where the hierarchical levels don't
conflict and the second thing is you get
rid of obstacles for them so that they
could come to you and say well I can't
do this because this is in the way your
job is to get it out of the way so that
they can move forward so it's a very
good way of can
exceptional izing yourself as a manager
so now part of there's obstacles that
you understand and those would
correspond to the micro levels of the
hierarchy right and then there's
obstacles that you don't understand and
when they come up they just blow apart
your whole plan so now associated with
that expected unexpected desired
undesired tool obstacle is a corollary
which is all the things that you're not
conceptualizing as tools or obstacles or
as things you don't know they're
irrelevant and that's a really useful
thing to know because it means that
whenever you're looking at the world
it's like the world is a sea of snakes
and you're only concentrating on one
snake at a time but then if you make a
mistake dealing with that single snake
what happens is you're neck deep in
snakes because all of the things the
thing is when you make a mistake and
this is a critical issue when you make a
mistake and you blow the framework
within which you're construing the world
the framework that narrows it for you
what happens is that all the things that
you've been ignoring become potentially
relevant and that's overwhelming and
that's partly why your body reacts as if
it's under tremendous stress so for
example you know how these things work
and again I think betrayal is the best
example if you have a partner and they
betray you then all the things that you
thought were true about the mark and all
those things you ignored as irrelevant
turned out not to be irrelevant at all
so you know maybe the person told you on
a twice weekly basis that they were too
busy studying to spend any time with you
and you know you just put that down into
the irrelevant zone after some coming to
terms with it and then you find out well
that is what they were doing during that
time and then the next question is well
what else did they tell you that wasn't
the way it was and the answer to that is
could it be anything it means every
single thing about your relationship
past present and future has now been
cast into the realm of potential
relevance and almost all the relevance
is negative and that's the descent into
chaos so that's the best way
conceptualize chaos is because what
happens is that your plan is what's
narrows the world for you and constrains
it makes most of it irrelevant the parts
that aren't relevant positive and the
negative elements relatively rare that's
what the intact hierarchical plan does
if you blow the hierarchical plan then
all your nice little subdivisions are
now irrelevant and every little monster
comes up to face you and that's the
descent into the underworld right and
people do not like that and no wonder
the reason they don't like that is
because it places them in a situation
that's so complex that it could easily
exceed their resources you know and so
for example one of the things that
happens to elderly people sometimes this
isn't precisely a betrayal is you know
they've been with someone for 40 years
and the person dies well the probability
that the partner will die in the
following year is much elevated compared
to their normal mortality and part of
that is they they just it's not that
they're grieving exactly although they
are what's happened is that one of the
fundamental axioms of the structures
that they use to encapsulate the world
has been blown out and everything comes
crashing down and so sometimes people
just don't have the resources to make it
through that they're just done you know
they don't know how to pick up the
pieces and start again you know and at
some point maybe god only knows at some
point maybe that's not what you do like
I don't know what you do after you're
married 75 years and your partner dies I
mean maybe you have a party if it's been
an absolutely dreadful marriage but but
in all likelihood you know it's it's
it's like a stroke that leaves you with
only half your body it's not clear that
you can recover from it so
that's a good question but I would say
what it's I don't think it's exactly
from the breaking of the framework I
think what happens is that the framework
breaks and then the person is cast into
such a state of physiological shock that
the shark actually starts to destroy
them so like if I stress you enough for
a reasonable length of time you're gonna
blow out at your weakest point and
that's a nice way to think about the
genetics of pathology of psychopathology
it's like everybody has a weakest point
you know it's like if you blow up a
balloon enough then it's gonna blow out
where it's the weakest well every one of
you has a weak point you know some of
you will have a threshold for that
weakness that's lower than others but
generally if I push hard enough on you
you're gonna something's going to happen
you're gonna you're going to get
hypoglycemic and then you're gonna eat
too much and then you're gonna become
obese or you're gonna turn to alcohol
because it's a really useful
anti-anxiety agent for you or you know
you're gonna develop some kind of other
stress-related illness maybe diabetes or
you know you're gonna develop an anxiety
disorder post-traumatic stress disorder
or maybe if you have a family history
towards psychosis you're going to
develop delusions and paranoia it
depends on it depends fundamentally on
exactly where where where you're most
flawed in your in your psycho
physiological makeup I don't think you
can necessarily predict how that's going
to happen although you can sometimes if
somebody has a loaded family history you
know and even with with with illnesses
like schizophrenia the standard models
are always stress dioceses there's a
preexistent vulnerability which will not
necessarily manifest itself unless the
push person is put under pressure you
know and it's interesting to think we
tend to think about stress in some sense
as a psychological phenomena but it's
not really a psychological phenomena
often even though it is related to the
way in which you construe the world the
complexity of the world is what stresses
people that hasn't psychological because
the world is complex the psychological
element is well are your
is your tool kit kit generally adequate
to deal with that complexity and some of
that has to do with subjective factors
you know when some of it has to do with
familial and social factors so okay so
I've construed normally as normal or
revolutionary and using Thomas Kuhns
terms and a normal bit of anomaly is one
that you can deal with without blowing
the framework within which you're
working and so and I hope everyone
understands this I know I've gone over
it a couple of times but it's it's a
very critical issue does it make sense
that the normally is normal if it only
disrupts subsidiary elements of the
plant it is is everyone clear about what
that means yes
there's a spectrum because there's a
hierarchy and we'll we'll look at the
hierarchy again but the idea is that the
stress the stress of the anomaly is
proportionate to its position in the
hierarchy of plans the most stressful
anomaly blows out your top-level plan
that's that's that's a near-death
experience it means everything that you
hold that would when I would be what
would happen if the economy collapsed
and your family was killed in a car
accident and your partner left you on
the same day it would be something like
that it's like the bottom drops out of
absolutely everything you know and that
does happen to people now and then and
we know what happens to people in
situations like that depending on their
level of resiliency because that that is
another issue but one of the most common
precipitants of severe depression is
unemployment you know and you might say
well is that psychological it's like no
I would say not really there's a
psychological element in that you might
not be as well prepared for a bout of an
unemployment as you could conceivably be
but if I have someone in my as a client
who's depressed and unemployed what I
try to do is treat the unemployment not
the depression because what the hell are
they gonna do you know how can you not
be depressed when you're looking at a
narrowing a world of narrowing
opportunities followed by losing your
house and ending up on the street it's
like that's it's not exactly a
psychological problem
yeah well I mean one of the thing is
it's like it's like being able to move
on your feet so let's say well let's say
you want to have it you the first
question is can you have a meaningful
life right because we're going to start
from the proposition that unvarnished
life is very dismal and dreadful right
so if you're not prepared for it we'll
just grind you up and that will be very
painful okay so we're gonna use that as
a baseline the baseline isn't that
you're gonna be secure and happy the
baseline is there isn't much of you
you're very fragile and things will
grind you into nothing
that's a Buddhist stance right because
the Buddhists say first dictum of
Buddhism is life is suffering the first
dictum isn't that life is happy so the
Buddhists basically say chaos is the
normative condition okay so fine so you
how do you do that how do you how do you
deal with that it's not how you fight
against it or defend against it I don't
think those are appropriate conceptual
conceptualizations it's not positive
illusions it's not defense mechanisms
it's none of that although you may also
use that what it is is do you have an
intimate relationship that works do you
have a family that's that's networked
well together and strong do you have
some sort of interesting occupation that
regularizes your schedule gives you
something productive to do on a
long-term basis is stable and productive
right do you have something that you
find engaging to do or maybe more than
one thing outside of work right and are
you compromising your mental and
physical health by doing any things that
are particularly stupid and you know one
of those I would like the top one of
those I would say is probably alcoholism
so if there's one thing you really want
to avoid that screws up your life it's
drinking too much it is unbelievably
dangerous so so the first thing we might
say is well let's optimize those well
the more you optimize those the more the
more pillars there are in your plan and
they're only somewhat correlated so
maybe you can lose one or maybe you can
even lose two it's going to knock you
down but it's not going to sink
you you know and then you might also
want to have variants on those plans to
some degree so like one of the things I
mentioned earlier is that it's always
nice to have an an alternative to your
current job at hand because it stops you
from being vulnerable it also stops you
from being a slave or a victim or maybe
even stops you from being a tyrant
because you've got some choice
so you diversify your your hierarchy of
plans essentially just like you do you
can think about it as stock market
investing in some sense it's a very
analogous idea you don't put all your
eggs in the same basket you diversify
across multiple portfolios so if one
sector gets knocked out hopefully
doesn't knock you completely out of the
game so so and that's partly what guide
you through in the in the future
authoring program - because it asks you
to consider what I think are the main
six dimensions of your life you know and
so one of the things I do when a client
comes is I just do a rough walkthrough
of those dimensions it's like does
anybody care if you're alive or dead you
know so do you have any friends do you
have anybody that loves you do you have
an intimate relationship however things
going with your family do you have a job
are you as educated as you are
intelligent do you have any room for
advancement in the future do you do
anything interesting outside of your job
and if the answer to all those is no
it's like you're not depressed
my friend you just are screwed really
it's like if someone like someone comes
to me and they're 40 and that's the
issue especially if they're also
drinking it's like Humpty Dumpty has hit
the floor and no one is going to put the
pieces together because it's just it's
too much it's too much people you know
what I mean it takes a whole lifetime to
put those things together that's not a
site that might have started as a
psychological problem but by the time
it's fully manifest in your 40 that's
not a psychological problem it's just a
complete catastrophe
well I think sometimes antidepressants
help and the reason they help is because
they actually buffer the stress response
so you know you're being ground down by
the world because essentially what you
are is you're you're you're not even in
the dominance hierarchy you're solo in
the dominance hierarchy that you're not
even in it right you're an outcast
fundamentally so maybe buffering the
stress response will help the person
just not die from that and then you
start with one thing you know it's like
you you lay out the potential areas for
approval improvement on the table and
you say well can we think of some small
steps that you might take in one or more
of those domains to start putting
something solid underneath your feet but
it's what happens I think is that as you
lose those pillars the way that problems
manifested themselves in your life
becomes networked and so you might make
progress here but some other catastrophe
that's looming over here is going to
knock you down you know so yeah
no it means that your your better
protected against being dreadfully
miserable and swamped than you would
otherwise be so I would say you have to
do those things before you can even
address the issue of being happy right
because if if you don't have if you
haven't establish yourself in one or one
or two of those domains say there's some
obvious things that you could do to
decrease the degree to which your life
is negative that you haven't yet done so
I would say you shouldn't even get to
the existential problem before you've
solved the practical problems and you
may find that if you solve the practical
problems the existential problems would
become bearable now not necessarily you
know because I might say well there's
another class of people and I would say
this is one of the pathologies of being
creative so if you're a high open person
and you have all those things that's not
going to be enough you're going to have
to pick another domain where you're
working on something that's positive and
somewhat revolutionary because like the
creative impulse is for someone who's
open we know it's a fundamental
personality dimension and I've watched I
have clients who are very high in
openness and others who aren't and if
the ones who are high in openness aren't
doing something creative then they're
like dead sticks there they can't live
properly so so you know that and I think
those are the people for example who
benefit particularly from depths of
psychological approaches especially
Union approaches I think that all of us
clients were high in openness because
I've watched my clients I'll try Union
ideas out on them and if they're high in
openness they work like a charm
it just fits right in with their psyche
but if they're conservative people
fundamentally conservative people Lo and
openness and high in conscientiousness
they it just doesn't click because the
Union approach is aesthetic and creative
and and lots of people aren't either of
those things so there was another
question yes
yeah but they fight especially if your
orderly you know because
conscientiousness is partly orderliness
and partly openness Hitler was like that
he was extremely orderly and extremely
high in openness and one of the ways he
solved that problems which was quite
interesting is that whenever there were
art exhibit submissions in Nazi Germany
there were two types there is the
approved Nazi art which was very
structured and conventional and you know
bordered on the propagandistic and there
was forbidden art which was really
chaotic and like often it was the
expressionist stuff for example which is
really emotionally expressive but
chaotic and Hitler would have both
exhibitions going on at the same time
and one of them would be forbidden and
the other would be approved you know so
but the problem with orderliness is that
you want everything to be in its
category and no wonder we've described
why that is but if you're open you're
always thinking well maybe there's a
better way of putting those things in a
category and that's a that's tough so
orderly open people are always at odds
with themselves you know so
yeah yeah well people like that are
often extremely successful right right
and it looks like industriousness is the
part of conscientiousness that predicts
long-term life success and orderliness
is the part that predicts conservative
political attitudes but low openness is
also associated with conservative
political attitudes so okay so okay so
the descent into the underworld that is
basically what occurs it can occur at
any level of your plant right from the
macro levels to the micro levels and
what happens is that it's a descent into
chaos if the unexpected thing is big
enough to invalidate the framework that
you're using to deal with the world at
that moment got it and then the degree
to which you feel negative emotion is
proportionate to the importance of that
plan to the organization of your
perception and action so you could think
about it as a you could think about what
you bring to bear on the world it's
almost like you can think about it as
how Google Maps manages it you know how
you can take Google Maps and obviously
it's a cybernetic intelligence right the
whole GPS search process because you say
I'm here and I'm going there and then it
maps a route out for you and if you go
off route it goes through a little
period of chaos and then it finds
another route
so it's really an intelligent system but
you notice that Google Maps is scalable
so you can look at probably if you're
going from here to Mississauga using a
map of Canada is the wrong map right you
want to scale the thing down until you
hit the level of resolution that both
that best represents the situation so
that you can move to where you want to
go you can scale up and down in it and
so finding out that the entire country
has been destroyed by nuclear bombs is
going to be a much bigger catastrophe in
relationship to your plan than finding
out that there's a few obstacles in the
street on your way to Mississauga that
haven't been marked on the map and so so
anyway so you're going to be
much more upset when the entire
superordinate that the low-resolution
plans are disrupted then when the
high-resolution plans are disrupted and
that's partly how your mind part of the
problem we're trying to solve here is
how upset should you be when something
you don't want happens and the answer to
that is that's virtually impossible to
compute but then the problem is you have
to compute it because if you don't
you'll burn yourself out with stress and
worry and and that's not psychological
that'll just kill you because it's
actually a physic cycle physiologically
damaging process so you have to
constrain it and so here are some of the
ways that you constrain it one you're
born with a baseline level of
neuroticism so if you're higher in
neuroticism you're going to think that
smaller things are more catastrophic
than someone who's lower in neuroticism
and you might say well who's right and
the answer is it depends completely on
the situation and it's random it's
fundamentally random and that's why
there's a normal distribution
on average we would say the typical
person is matched to the typical
environment but sometimes the terrified
people are going to be right and
sometimes the people that you can't
bother no matter what you do are going
to be right okay so that's one its
crapshoot the second is where are you in
a dominance hierarchy because one of the
things your brain is trying to
understand is how should you regard
yourself as an active and competent
organism when you're facing problems
that you can't compute and the answer to
that is we're not going to solve that
we're going to distribute the problem
into the social network and we're going
to let everyone else solve it and so if
you rise up in the dominance hierarchy
your brain reacts as if the dominance
hierarchy structure which is composed of
many many brains has run its
computations and decided that you're
pretty damn competent and so the way
your brain responds to that is it cranks
up your serotonin production and it
decreases your neuroticism and it's
perfectly reasonable computation because
a if everybody says you're competent
you're competent enough so that you're
going to get more rewarded for your
competence than other people are and
that's going to make you more secure in
your job that's going to make you more
Herbal and in demand among other people
and that's going to give you access to
resources you wouldn't otherwise have so
and then there's a there's a correlated
element to that which is sort of your
level of self esteem although that's
very much associated with with
neuroticism people with high self esteem
generally have low levels of negative
emotion it's not it's not clear that
those are separable phenomena all right
what time is it
2:45 all right well let's stop for 10
minutes okay and we'll yeah let's stop
for 10 minutes